<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A forme of catechizing set downe by questions and answers. Wherein, the principall grounds of Christian religion are deliuered. By Edward Elton, preacher of the vvord of God in the parish of St. Mary Magdalens in Barmondsey nere London. 1. Concerning God. 2. Concerning man, his creation, fall, and state of corruption. 3. Concerning mans deliuerance by Christ. 4. Concerning the meanes of being partakers of Christ and his benefits. 5. Concerning the meanes of obtayning faith, and the good things that follow faith. 6. Concerning the estate of man in death, after death, particular iudgment, and the last and generall iudgement.</title>
            <author>Elton, Edward, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18859</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18859)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 884:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A forme of catechizing set downe by questions and answers. Wherein, the principall grounds of Christian religion are deliuered. By Edward Elton, preacher of the vvord of God in the parish of St. Mary Magdalens in Barmondsey nere London. 1. Concerning God. 2. Concerning man, his creation, fall, and state of corruption. 3. Concerning mans deliuerance by Christ. 4. Concerning the meanes of being partakers of Christ and his benefits. 5. Concerning the meanes of obtayning faith, and the good things that follow faith. 6. Concerning the estate of man in death, after death, particular iudgment, and the last and generall iudgement.</title>
                  <author>Elton, Edward, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Ralph Mab, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Greyhound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:1"/>
            <p>A FORME OF CATECHIZING, ſet downe by Queſtions and Anſwers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein, the principall grounds òf</hi> Chriſtian Religion are deliuered.</p>
            <p>By EDWARD ELTON Preacher of the word of God, in the Pariſh of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> in <hi>Barmondſey</hi> nere LONDON.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Concerning God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Concerning Man, his creation, fall, and ſtate of corruption.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Concerning mans deliuerance by Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Concerning the meanes of being parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt and his benefits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Concerning the meanes of obtayning faith, and the good things that follow faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Concerning the eſtate of man in death, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, particular iudgment, and the laſt and generall iudgement.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Ralph Mab,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Churchyard at the ſigne of the Greyhound. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE chiefeſt thing a man or woman ſhould deſire and ſeek after, is, how to liue and dye comfortably: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>Now this can neuer be attayned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man know God aright, and haue a right knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh: 17.3.</note> whom he hath ſent.</p>
            <p>The way to true comfort and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes both in this life and for euer, is, to know God to be our Father in Chriſt by the reuelation of his ſpirit, according to his word. And this knowledge is not in vs by nature, and one ſpeciall meanes to attaine vnto it is inſtruction in the grounds of Religion.</p>
            <p>I will draw that I purpoſe to deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:18859:3"/> in this kinde of exerciſe, to certaine gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heads and grounds of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, needfull to be knowne and beleeued of all Chriſtians, and handle theſe grounds by way of Qu ſtion and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they may the better be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
            <p>Now then, the first ground, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Religion, I purpoſe to handle, ſhall be concerning God, what wee are to conceiue and beleeue concerning God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:3"/>
            <head>A Forme of Catechizing, ſet <hi>downe by Questions and Anſwers;</hi> Wherein the principall grounds of Chriſtian Religion are deliuered.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion. <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God is a ſpirit, or ſpirituall ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Joh: 4.24.</note> moſt wiſe, moſt holy, eternall and infinite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How are we perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that there is ſuch a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Beſides the euidence and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Scripture, by theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> By the creating and making of the world and all things in it: and eſpecially the ſoule of man.<note place="margin">Rom: 1.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">Zachar. 12.1.</note> by the works of Gods prouidence, and chiefly his fearefull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.16. Pſal. 58.10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> on monſtrous and notorious ſinners in this life.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Thirdly, by common conſent of all
<pb facs="tcp:18859:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nations, who rather worſhip any God or gods, than none at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. Epheſ. <hi>2.12. The Gentiles were without God in the world.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. <hi>The meaning is, they were without the true God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Fourthly, by the accuſation &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of conſcience: a man that commits any ſinne in ſecret, his conſcience natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally checking him, accuſing and terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him for the ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15. Iſai: 33.14.</note> and as it were drawing him before a iudgement ſeat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many Gods be there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.4. 1. Tim. 2.5. 1. Cor. 8.6.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely one and no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect. Pſalm. <hi>82.1. God ſtandeth in the aſſembly of Gods.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. <hi>The word is there taken for Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Magiſtrates, becauſe they ſtand in Gods place or roome.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How is this one God to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not by framing any image of him in our mindes:<note place="margin">Deut: 4.16.</note> neither can we conceiue him in his glorious nature, but we are to conceiue God,<note place="margin">Iudg: 13.18. 1. Tim. 6.16.</note> as he hath reuealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his word, by his properties and works.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What be the chiefe properties of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, he is moſt wiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God.</note> 
               <hi>Iob 12.13. Rom. 16.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is that wiſdom of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is that by which God doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and perfectly know himſelfe, and all other things aright: and knoweth the nature, reaſon, and cauſes of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the ſecond propertie of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is moſt holy, <hi>Iſai: 6.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is that holineſſe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a moſt abſolute &amp; perfect pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of all Gods properties and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes:<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.6.</note> and it appeares in that he is moſt iuſt, and mercifull vnto his creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the third propertie of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is eternall, <hi>Iſaiah 41.4. Reuel. 1.4.</hi> And that euery way, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or end of daies. Angells and the Soules of men be eternall, but not euery way, though they ſhall neuer die, yet had they a beginning, and they are eternall not abſolutely but by participation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the fourth propertie of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is infinite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many waies is God infinite?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two waies: Firſt, in preſence. Secondly, in power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.7. 1. King. 8.27. Jer. 23.24. Deut. 10.17.</note>In preſence. He being preſent in all places filling heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>In power. He being able to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he will. <hi>Pſal. 115.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. <hi>God cannot lie, Tit. 1.2. or deny himſelfe, 2. Tim. 2.13. therefore he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do all things.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. <hi>To lie or to denie himſelfe are works of impotency and weaknes, and not of power, and therefore cannot befall God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For works of impotencie, or things contrary to the nature of God, as to deſtroy himſelfe, or not beget his Sonne from all eternitie. Or things that imply contradiction: as to make a truth falſe, or that which is not, to be, at the ſame time, cannot befall God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many wayes is Gods power taken or diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two wayes, it is either abſolute or actuall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is his abſolute power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3.9. Phil. 3.21.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That by which hée is able to doe more then either he doth, or will do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is his actuall power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 135.6.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That by which hee cauſeth all
<pb facs="tcp:18859:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> things to bee which he willeth, and doth whatſoeuer he will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the workes of God by which we are to conceiue him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two, creation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How are we to conceiue of God in reſpect of creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10.12. Acts 4.24.</note> That he is the moſt mighty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the world, and of euery thing that hath a being in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. <hi>There bee many euils and hurtfull things in the world, as venemous and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull beaſts, hearbes, and ſuch like, yea, euill ſpirits, the Diuell and his Angels, did God create them?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <hi>Yes, God did create all theſe things,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.20.25.</note> 
               <hi>but wee muſt vnderſtand, that God made not poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull creatures ſo at the firſt, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo by the fall of man. Hurtfull and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull creatures which now are for the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and puniſhment of man for ſinne, ſhould not haue beene ſo, if man had not fallen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againe, <hi>God made the Deuill and euill ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, at the firſt very good and glorious ſpirits, but they willingly and of their owne accord,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 6.</note> 
               <hi>fell from that puritie in which they were created,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſo their being is from the will of God, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir being euill is from their owne wils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Did God make ſinne, ſickneſſes, diſeaſes and death, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: theſe bee no creatures of God, we finde not the making of theſe in the firſt creation of all things. Sin is no Creature of God, but the deſtruction of Gods Image, which is a Creature: and ſickneſſes, diſeaſes, and death came into the world by ſinne, and follow ſinne. And though they come from God as correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Rom. 5 12. 1. Sam. 2.6.</note> exerciſes or puniſhments: yet are they no Creatures, as things that haue a being in the world, but rather as deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſuch things as haue being.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the worke of creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen 1. Heb. 11.3.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the making of all things in their ſeuerall kindes, of nothing, by the mighty power of God in the firſt ſix daies of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. <hi>Man was made of the duſt of the earth,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>fiſhes of the water, beaſts and foules of the earth, woman of man: How then did God make all things of nothing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <hi>God made the firſt matter of all things of nothing, &amp; then of that matter were all things formed.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the ſecond work by which we are to conceiue God in our mindes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The preſeruation of all things created by his ſpecial prouidence, we are to conceiue him in our mindes, as the moſt wiſe and mighty Preſeruer of all things created. <hi>1. Pet. 3.19.</hi> God is a faithfull Creator, he did not onely make heauen and earth and all things in them, and ſo leaue them; but he by his wiſe prouidence and mighty power doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and gouerne the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is that worke of preſeruation of all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the hand and power of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 91. Ioh. 5.17.</note> continually exerciſed in ſuſtaining and diſpoſing of all things created.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How doth God ſuſtaine all things created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> Hee vpholdeth them all in their being by his mighty word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How doth God diſpoſe of all things created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10 29.30. Prou. 16.33.</note> Hee guideth and employeth them to good ends and vſes, yea, euen the leaſt things, as the flie, the gnat, and ſuch like: ſo that nothing comes to paſſe by
<pb facs="tcp:18859:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> chance, not ſo much as a little ſparrow hoppeth or falleth on the ground without the prouidence &amp; diſpoſing hand of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How know you that God ordereth and gouerneth all things by his moſt wiſe and mighty power, and by his ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Beſides the euidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.26.</note> by experience, we ſée that meat and drinke being voyd of life, yet preſerue the life of man:<note place="margin">Matth. 4.4.</note> cloathing being voyd of heat, yet it kéeps the body warme, which could not bee but by the ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God giuing vertue to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What are wee further to conceiue and beleeue concerning God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That in one ſimple and vndiuided God-head, in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> diuine eſſence there be thrée diſtinct perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and that theſe thrée perſons are equall in eternity and glory, that they are alike eternall, none of the thrée pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſons being afore or after another in time, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at they are equall in all things that bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g to the nature of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q How is the Trinity of perſons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By theſe places of Scripture, <hi>Mat. 3.16.17. cap. 28. verſ. 19. 2. Cor. 13.13. 1: Ioh. 5.7. There bee three which beare record in heauen, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit, and theſe three are one.</hi> In that he ſaith thrée, he noteth the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the perſons: and in ſaying one, he ſheweth the vnity of the eſſence, that in one vndiuided God-head there bee thrée diſtinct perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.7. Ioh. 5.26.</note> In reſpect of order hee is the firſt perſon in the God-head without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being of himſelfe and from none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and giuing perſonall being to his Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the Son?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16. Ioh. 5.26. Prou. 8.22. to 32. verſe.</note> Hee is the ſecond perſon in the God-head, hauing perſonall being from the Father, of whom he is begotten from all eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.26. Rom. 8.9.</note> He is the third perſon in the God-head, hauing perſonall being from the Father and the Son: he proceeding from them both from all eternity.<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> He is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſpirit of Chriſt: whence wee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:18859:8"/> and that truely, that hee proceedeth no leſſe from the Sonne, then from the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are theſe three perſons three ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Gods, as three perſons amongſt men, are three ſeuerall men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>A.</hi> No: The thrée perſons are but one God. Becauſe the diuine eſſence is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and admits no diuiſion: and the whole diuine eſſence is in euery one of the perſons; which are not ſeuered, but onely diſtinguiſhed one from another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How are wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o conceiue the three perſons in the Godh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad diſtinct one from another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two waies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in the manner of perſonall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which ech perſon hath proper to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. As that.</p>
            <p>The Father is the perſon which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets; the Sonne the perſon who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father; &amp; the Holy Ghoſt the perſon, who procéedes from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in the manner of working in the creatures. For the Scriptures aſcribes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18859:8"/>
            <p>To the Father the beginning of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.17.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To the Sonne, wiſdome and counſell, and the diſpenſation of the worke, <hi>Ioh. 1.3.</hi> All things were made by it (that is) the Word, the ſecond perſon in the God-head. <hi>Heb. 1.2. By whom alſo he made the worlds.</hi> Hence he is called <hi>Wiſdome, <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Holy Ghoſt, vertue,<note place="margin">Iob 26.13. 1. Cor. 12.11.</note> and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and efficacy of operation. In a word, God the Father, in the Son, by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt worketh all things. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is beyond all reach and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man, yet to bee beléeued as that which God hath reuealed in his word, for our ſaluation which cannot ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond generall Principle ſhall bee concerning Man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Man.</note> what wee are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and beleeue touching man, and our ſelues in particular.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Of all viſible Creatures which is the heifeſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Man: for in man aboue all other
<pb facs="tcp:18859:9"/> viſible Creatures the Lord ſets foorth the glory of his wiſedome,<note place="margin">Prou. 8.31. Pſa. 8.5.6.7.8.</note> power and goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was the ſtate and condition of man at the firſt, in his firſt creation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It was an holy &amp; an happy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a ſtate of innocency &amp; a ſtate of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtood that holy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that hee was frée from ſinne, and created after Gods owne image and likeneſſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.27 Gen. 5.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was that image of GOD in which man was created at the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It was a conformity of man to God,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.10. Epheſ. 4.24.</note> euen a conformity of all the powers of the ſoule of man to the will of God, ſtanding in wiſedome and holineſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was the wiſdome that was in man at the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A perfect knowledge of God his Creator, and of his will to bee obeyed: and of his wiſedome and will touching the particular Creatures. For <hi>Adam</hi> named them according to their natures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was that holineſſe that was in man at the firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It was a conformity of the will and affections and the whole diſpoſition of man in body and ſoule, to the will of God his Creator.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q Wherein ſtood that happie condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man in his firſt creation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In thrée things.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, In a bleſſed communion which man had with the true God, with whom he had daily, and as it were familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation: and God did many waies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale himſelfe and his glory to him, and this is apparant by Gods familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, In dominion ouer the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.28.</note> an example whereof wee haue in <hi>Gen. 2.19.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.19.</note> when all creatures preſented themſelues before him to receiue their names from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, In a body endued with beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſtrength and immortality, and that his body was immortall,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.25. Rom. 5.12.</note> there is no queſtion ſeeing death came in by ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What employment had man in his firſt ſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Twofold, particular and outward, to till and dreſſe the garden.<note place="margin">Gen. 2.25.</note> And gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:18859:10"/> and ſpirituall,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.7.</note> to worſhip and ſerue God his Creator: to which he was fitted of God with fréedome of will and ability for perfect obedience, hauing the morall law written in his heart by nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth that appeare?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by the effect of the law in his heart, for man hauing ſinned, the guilt of his conſcience forced him to hid himſelfe from Gods preſence.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by the remainders of the Law of God in all mankinde, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not the Law of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.14.15</note> are a law vnto themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Did man continue in that ſtate in which he was created?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: he left it and fell from righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to ſinne.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How was it that man loſt his firſt ſtate and fell from righteouſneſſe to ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God ſuffering Sathan to tempt him, and leauing him to the liberty and mutability of his owne will: he fell into ſinne, eating of the forbidden fruit: hence Sathan is called by Chriſt, a murtherer from the beginning.<note place="margin">Gen. 3 1. &amp;c. Iob. 3.44.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How did Sathan tempt man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He vſed the Serpent a ſubtil beaſt as his inſtrument, and ſpake out of him,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.1 3.4.5</note> firſt to the woman, and after by her to the man,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.3.</note> pretending greater loue to them, and greater care of their good then was in God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How did man and woman our firſt parents yeeld to temptation, being created good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.6. Eccleſ. 7.31.</note> Being left of God to the libertie and mutability of their owne will, they voluntarily enclined to that euill where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they were tempted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the ſtate of man, being fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from his firſt eſtate in which hee was created?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſtate of corruption and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is that ſtate of corruption following the fall of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the loſſe of the image of God in which man was created at the firſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3. Epheſ. 4.22. Ioh. 3.6.</note> and the image of Sathan ſuccéeding in the place or roome of it, ſo that man in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tate can doe nothing but ſinne, and this the Scripture cals the <hi>image of Adam.
<pb facs="tcp:18859:11"/> The olde man. The fleſh.</hi> And in a word, it is the ſtate of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sinne is any ſwaruing from the Law of God,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.4. Rom. 7 7. Gal. 3.10.</note> though it be but in the leaſt want of that which the Law requireth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How many ſorts of ſins be there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, originall and actuall. Sin is either the corruption of nature, or the euill actions that procéed from thence, as the fruits of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the corruption of nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.7. Iam. 1.14.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that corruption that is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from our firſt parents by naturall generation, called luſt or concupiſcence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherin ſtandeth that corruption?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7 18.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in an vtter diſability and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to that which is good.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note>Secondly, in a proaneſſe to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. In whom is that corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In all men and women none excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, diſcending from <hi>Adam</hi> by naturall generation.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.23. Gal. 3.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is it, that all men and women
<pb facs="tcp:18859:11"/> are defiled with the corruption of nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Through the infidelity and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of our firſt Parents in eating the forbidden fruit,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.12.18.19.</note> all men being guilty of that ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are all men guilty of that ſin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe they were in the loynes of our firſt Parents,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.9.10.</note> from whom they ſhould by courſe of nature deſcend.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe our firſte Parents were by Gods appoyntment, to ſtand or fall, not as ſingular perſons onely,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19. 1. Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.22.</note> but alſo as heads and rootes of man-kind, and as publike perſons repreſenting al man-kinde. As wee ſée Noblemen and great men by treaſon doe not onely hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but ſtraine their bloud alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How then is all mankinde in the ſtate of ſinne ſince the fall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus; euery one naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending of <hi>Adam</hi> is guilty of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, it being imputed to him,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19. Pſalm. 51.5. Epheſ. 2.1.</note> and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conceiued and borne in originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and is by nature dead in ſinne, and hath in him the ſeed of all ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is. Is originall corruption found in all and euery man equally?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, it is: for that which is borne by naturall generation is nothing but corruption;<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.6.</note> Originall ſinne is not in ſome men more, and in ſome men leſſe, but it is in euery man equally, as all men doe equally from <hi>Adam</hi> participate the nature of man,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> and are equally the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q Doth this corruption of nature breake forth and ſhew it ſelfe equally and alike in all naturall men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: it doth not, though originall corruption be found equally and alike in all men naturally, and all men haue in their corrupt nature the ſeedes of euerie ſinne, yet doth God for the good of human ſociety, limit mans corruption, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine many from notorious crimes,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.3.4.4</note> by their naturall temper, by feare of ſhame and puniſhment, deſire of honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. In what part of man is this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 6.5. 1. Theſſ 5.23.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the whole man, both in bodie and ſoule, and in euery part and member of the body, and in all the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:12"/>
               <p>Now there being many powers and faculties of the ſoule, as the minde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, will and affections, the next Queſtion is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the naturall corruption of the minde of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is both the dulneſſe and the blindneſſe of the minde concerning hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, whereby the minde is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ignorant of ſpirituall things,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14. 2 Cor: 3.5. Epheſ. 4.18.</note> concerning the true worſhip of God, and eternall happineſſe: and is of it ſelfe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnable to conceiue them.</p>
               <p>And it is alſo the readineſſe and fitnes of the minde to conceiue euill things,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.30. Epheſ. 4.17. Iſaiah 5.20. &amp; 44.20.</note> whereby the minde is caried to error and vaine imaginations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the naturall corruption of the conſcience of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit: 1.15.</note> It is the impureneſſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtands that impureneſſe of the naturall conſcience of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things: either in want of remorſe, in a benummednes and vnfée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of the conſcience in reſpect of ſinne,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.19.</note> the conſcience being benummed
<pb facs="tcp:18859:13"/> with ſinne: or in the ſtirring of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the conſcience ſenſibly either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing or excuſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is the ſtirring of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence impure in the ſenſible accuſation of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two waies: firſt, in accuſing for well-doing,<note place="margin">Col: 2.21.22.</note> as ſometimes the naturall conſcience doth; this we may ſée in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Idolaters. Secondly, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing for ſinne,<note place="margin">Iſai. 29.23.</note> and continually turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and terrifying a man for ſinne,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.20.21.</note> and giuing him no reſt, no eaſe, nor peace at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is the ſtirring conſcience im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure in excuſing ſenſibly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two waies likewiſe: firſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing when it ſhould rather accuſe,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.19.20.</note> as when a man liues a ciuill honeſt life, frée from groſſe ſinnes, as murther, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſuch like, and ſerues God out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, then excuſing him and falſly tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that he is iuſt before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat of God, and this excuſing conſcience is found in moſt men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, excuſing for doing that which is euill:<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.2.</note> as when men thinke they
<pb facs="tcp:18859:13"/> doe God good ſeruice, in excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and killing the ſeruants of God: or as the Papiſts doe, for ſaying ouer ſo many <hi>Creeds,</hi> ſo many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> ſo many <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and ſuch like, thinke they ſhall be heard for their vaine repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions and babling in prayer.<note place="margin">Math: 6.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q What is the naturall corruption of the will of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is both the impotencie of the will,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.13. Ioh: 6.44.</note> whereby the will is vtterly vnable of it ſelfe to will or luſt after that which is truly good. And it is alſo the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie and rebellion of the will, whereby it is altogether auerſe and ſtriuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which is truly good,<note place="margin">Gen: 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iob 15.16.</note> and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling only that which is euill continually.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the naturall corruption of the affections of man, as of loue, ioy, hope, deſire, and ſuch like?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the diſorder of them,<note place="margin">Iam: 4.1. 1 King: 21.4. &amp; 22.8.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they eſchew that which is good, and purſue and follow after that which is euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the naturall corruption of the parts and members of the body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is both a fitnes in them, as por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:18859:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> to let ſinne in,<note place="margin">Mat: 5, 28, 29, 30. Iſai: 59.7. Ier: 9.3. Rom: 3.13.</note> and to conuey it to the ſoule from outward obiects and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; and a fitnes in them, as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to execute ſin and to practiſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus we haue heard what the corruption of nature is: the next Queſtion is,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is actuall ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a fruit of originall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Iam: 1.15. Mat: 15.19.</note> and it is a particular and actuall breach of Gods law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is actuall ſin diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into inward and outward. It is either in the inward faculties of the ſoule, as the minde, or will and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or in the outward members of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the actuall ſinne of the minde?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen: 6.5. Pro: 6.18. Ioh: 13.2. 1 Chro: 21.1. Act: 5.3.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the euill thought or intent of the minde, which comes either by the conceiuing of the minde it ſelfe, or by Satans ſuggeſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the actuall ſin of the will and affections?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is euery motion, luſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,<note place="margin">Gal: 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.24.</note> ſtirring in the heart contrary to Gods law.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is outward actuall ſinne in the outward members of the body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that which is committed by the members of the body, concurring with the faculties of the ſoule,<note place="margin">1 Cor: 6.18. 1 Theſſ. 4.4.</note> as by hands, eyes, eares, tongue, féete, &amp;c. yea ſometimes by the whole body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is actuall ſin effected?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two waies: either by omiſſion or commiſſion: it is effected either by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that which ought to be done, or by committing that euill that is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den &amp; ought not to be done,<note place="margin">Iſai: 3.8.</note> whether it be inwardly in minde, will or affection, or outwardly in word or déede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the differences of ſinne actually committed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are many: but eſpecially theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a partaking with others in ſin,<note place="margin">Mar: 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. Act. 22.20. Rom: 1.31. 1 Tim: 5.22.</note> by conſent, approbation, counſell, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, enticement, or the like.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a ſinning ignorantly, or of a conſcience miſinformed<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal: 19.12. 1 Cor. 8.7. 1 Tim: 1.13.</note>.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a ſinning of knowledge through infirmitie<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note>.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Pſal: 19.13. Pſal. 50.17.</note> a ſinning preſumptuouſly
<pb facs="tcp:18859:15"/> vpon knowledge.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, a ſinning vpon knowledge ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately and on ſet malice againſt God: and to this belongs the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">Heb: 6.6. &amp; 10.28, 29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto of the ſtate of corruption follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fall of man: Now followes the ſtate of miſerie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the ſtate of miſerie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the fall of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a continuall ſubiection to the curſe of God,<note place="margin">Gen: 2.17. Deut. 27.26. Galat. 3.10.</note> whereby man by the iuſt ſentence of God, is continually ſubiect and lyable to Gods curſe for ſinne, and that in this life, in the end of this life, and after this life is ended: and this was ſignified by expelling our firſt Parents out of Paradiſe after the fall.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein is man for ſinne ſubiect and lyable to the curſe of God in this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In his body and outward eſtate, in his ſoule, and in the whole man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of God due to man, and wherevnto he is ſubiect in his body and outward eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 28.21.22.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is all manner of outward griefe,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:15"/> anguiſh, vexation, trouble and want, as ſicknes, diſeaſes, aches, paines, ſhame,<note place="margin">Mala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 2.2. Pſal: 69.22.</note> ſeruitude, penurie, and ſuch like; yea bleſſings and good things curſed to him, and turned to ſnares.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of God due to man, and wherevnto he is ſubiect in his ſoule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is all manner of inward diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, trouble, griefe and want in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of his ſoule,<note place="margin">Rom: 1.28. Deut. 28.28. Leuit: 26.36.</note> as blindneſſe of minde, hardnes of heart, horror of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, madnes, aſtoniſhment of heart, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of God due vnto man, and wherevnto the whole man is ſubiect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a bondage vnder Satan, whereby man is ſubiect to the regiment of Satan, and Satan is his Lord and Maſter:<note place="margin">2 Cor: 4.4. Epheſ: 2.2. 2 Tim: 2.26.</note> hence Satan is called <hi>the God of this world;</hi> and <hi>the Prince that ruleth in the ayre,</hi> and <hi>the ſpirit that worketh in the children of diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How ſhall a man know that he is thus in bondage vnder Satan?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If he take delight in the euill mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:18859:16"/> Satan puts into his heart, and doe yéeld to them with pleaſure,<note place="margin">Ioh: 8.44. 1 Ioh: 3.5.</note> expreſſing them in his life and conuerſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of God wherunto a man is ſubiect in the end of this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the power of corporall death, the death of the body, whereby the ſoule is ſeuered from the body.<note place="margin">Rom: 5.12. Gen: 2.17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of God due vnto man, and wherevnto he is ſubiect after this life is ended?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is eternall death of body and ſoule in the fire of hell, called the ſecond death, which is a finall ſeparation from the comfortable preſence of God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Mat: 7.23. Mat: 25.41. 2 Theſſ. 1.9. Reuel. 20.6.</note> Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, and a ſenſe and féeling of Gods wrath in that ſeparation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Principle, touching Mans deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from that damnable eſtate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What meanes of deliuerance is there,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Principle.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>whereby a man may ſcape this dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God of his infinite mercy hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a Sauiour and Deliuerer to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When was that Sauiour and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerer giuen to Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was ſet apart to that office in Gods decrée from euerlaſting,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.5. Epheſ. 1.4.</note> from all eternitie, but promiſed and propounded immediately after the fall in Paradiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15. Galat. 4.4. 1. Tim: 2.6.</note> and manifeſted and exhibited in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Who is that Sauiour and deliuerer giuen to man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Mat: 1.21. Act. 4.12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The eternall Sonne of God made man like to vs in all things, ſin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and ſo God and man in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Matth. 1.23. Ioh. 1.14. Rom: 9.5. Iſai: 9.6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How proue you that Ieſus Chriſt is GOD?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beſides the plentifull teſtimonie of Scripture, it is cleare by his many miracles, by his knowing the hearts of men,<note place="margin">Rom: 1.4,</note> and eſpecially by raiſing of himſelf from the dead, together with the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his goſpell from time to time, not by carnall meanes, nor by humane power or policie, but only by the power
<pb facs="tcp:18859:17"/> of his ſpirit,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.11.</note> and patient ſuffering of his Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How proue you that Ieſus Chriſt was very man like to vs in all things, ſinne only excepted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beſides the teſtimonie of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is cleare by many experiments, eſpecially by his partaking of humane infirmities common to mans nature; as to be hungry, thirſtie, weary, ſad, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, angry, ignorant of ſome things, &amp; ſuch like, and by his ſuffering of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How could Chriſt be very man, and yet be without ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he was not begotten af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ordinarie courſe of nature, by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall generation, but as man he was formed of the only ſubſtance of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> his mother, and that ſubſtance was ſanctified in the conception,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.34.35.</note> that is, ſeuered from all ſtaine of ſinne, by the power of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherefore was it needfull that Chriſt ſhould be man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For two reaſons: Firſt, that hée might die and ſuffer the puniſhment due to ſin,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14. Philip. 2.7, 8.</note> which the Godhead could not do.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:17"/>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3. 1. Pet. 2.24.</note> that he might appeaſe Gods wrath in the ſame nature, wherein God was offended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherefore was it needfull that Chriſt ſhould be God alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For two reaſons likewiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that he might vphold his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in ſuffering, and vanquiſh death.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the doings and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of his manhood might be of infinite worth and vertue.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> hence the Church is ſaid to be purchaſed by the blood of God.<note place="margin">Act: 20.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are we further to know and beleeue touching Chriſt his being God and Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the diſtinction of his two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. and</p>
               <p>Secondly, the vnion of them.</p>
               <p>That his two natures are diſtinct one from another, and that they are alſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and make but one perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are we to know and beleeue touching the diſtinction of the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Chriſt, his Godhead and his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That there is a reall diſtinction of
<pb facs="tcp:18859:18"/> thoſe two natures,<note place="margin">Mat: 26.39. Ioh: 10.17.18 Act: 3.21. 2 Cor: 13.4.</note> without any mixture of the one with the other, and without any conuerſion or turning of the one into the other, and that the eſſentiall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and actions of both natures remaine diſtinct one from another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are we to know and beleeue touching the vnion of Chriſt his two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, his Godhead and his manhood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That they are vnited by perſonall vnion, that the Godhead and manhood in Chriſt make but one perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is that perſonall vnion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the aſſuming of the humane nature into the perſon of the Sonne of God, ſo as the manhood being not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in it ſelfe, is receiued into vnitie of perſon with the ſecond perſon in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<note place="margin">Ioh: 1.14. Heb: 2.16.</note> and doth wholy and only ſubſiſt in the ſame: this is a myſterie of godlineſſe ſo called. <hi>1. Tim: 3.16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto of the perſon of Christ, now come we to the office.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the office of Ieſus Chriſt being God and man in one perſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is his Mediatorſhip to be the
<pb facs="tcp:18859:18"/> only Mediator betwéene God and man,<note place="margin">Iſai: 42.6. &amp; 49.8. 1 Tim: 2.5. Heb. 9.15.</note> to ratifie and confirme the couenant of grace, and to make perfect reconciliation betwéene God and man, being parties infinitely and euery way diſagréeing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How was Ieſus Chriſt fitted for the accompliſhment of that office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was annoynted of his Father, and ſo made fit for the perfect accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: hence he is called <hi>(Chriſt)</hi> which ſignifieth annoynted, &amp; this was figured and ſhadowed out in the annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Prophets, Prieſts, and Kings in the time of the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Was Chriſt annoynted with viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and materiall oyle as they were?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No:<note place="margin">Ioh: 3.34. Act: 10.38. Heb. 1.9.</note> but with the graces and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, and that moſt fully and without meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſeuerall functions and offices of Chriſt as he is Mediator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are thrée: namely his
<list>
                     <item>Propheticall,</item>
                     <item>Prieſtly, and</item>
                     <item>Kingly</item>
                  </list> office.</p>
               <p>Chriſt was annoynted of his Father to
<pb facs="tcp:18859:19"/> be the onely Prophet, Prieſt and King of his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the propheticall office of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the office of reuealing the will of God,<note place="margin">Iſa: 61.1. Math: 17.5. Ioh: 1.18. Mat: 23.8, 10.</note> and the meanes of ſaluation to his Church in all ages, Chriſt hauing béene, now being, and euer ſhall be the only Teacher of his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q How did Chriſt performe this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and how doth he now performe it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two waies.</p>
               <p>Firſt outwardly, by the miniſtery of his word,<note place="margin">Math. 23.37. 1. Pet: 3.19. 2. Pet. 1.21.</note> as before his incarnation, by the Prophets and Teachers of the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>And in the daies of his fleſh in his own perſon.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.3. 2 Cor. 5.19.20. Eph. 4.11.12.</note> And ſince his aſcenſion by his Apoſtles and Miniſters called and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.45. Act. 16.14. 1. Cor. 3.6, 7.</note>Secondly, inwardly, by the operation and teaching of his Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the prieſtly office of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that whereby Chriſt hath and doth reconcile God to his elect,<note place="margin">Heb 5.9. Heb. 7.24, 25.</note> he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all thoſe things to God, for them, whereby they may come to eternall life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtandeth the performance of the offiice of Chriſt his Prieſthood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In doing thrée things for Gods choſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the fulfilling of the law of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> and performing perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtood that perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, In the puritie of his humane nature, he being conceiued and borne pure and holy, voide of all ſinne. and</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, In the obedience of his whole life,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.22, 28 Rom. 8.3, 4.</note> he doing all that the law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him for Gods choſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the ſecond thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh: 1.29. 1 Cor. 5.7. Heb. 9.14.26.</note> It is the offering of himſelfe vnto God his Father a ſacrifice holy &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, thereby appeaſing his wrath for all their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How was Chriſt offered in ſacrifice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As he was man conſiſting of body and ſoule?<note place="margin">Iſa: 53 10. Heb. 10.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How often did Chriſt ſacrifice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Onely once and no more. <hi>Heb. 9.28. Heb. 10.12.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What manner of death did Chriſt ſuffer, when he ſacrificed himſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A death on the Croſſe, an accurſed death,<note place="margin">Luk: 22 44 Ioh: 12.27. Gal. 3.13.</note> whereby his ſoule was not only ſeuered from his body, but he felt alſo the extreame horror &amp; moſt bitter pangs of hell in his ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the third thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Chriſt his entring into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and there appearing before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 34. 1. Ioh. 2.1.</note> continually making interceſſion for all the faithfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. After what manner doth Chriſt make interceſſion in heauen for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not by proſtrating himſelfe and vttering words to his Father, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp a prayer or ſupplication to his Father: but by preſenting himſelfe and the ſacrifice of himſelfe once offered vpon the Croſſe, and the infinite and invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able merit of that ſacrifice before the eyes of his Father,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.24. Ioh: 17.24.</note> willing as he is God and man, and deſiring as he is man that his Father would accept of his perfect
<pb facs="tcp:18859:20"/> ſatisfaction: for all that are giuen vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the fruite and benefit of Chriſt his interceſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is this: it kéepes euery true beléeuer in the ſtate of grace, and in the fauour of God continually, and it makes their weake prayers, and imperfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience acceptable and pleaſing to God by a ſpeciall and continuall application of the merit of his death and obedience to them. <hi>1. Ioh. 2.2. 1. Pet. 2.5.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2. 1. Pet. 2.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the Kingly office of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that, whereby Chriſt exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the power giuen him of his Father ouer all things, diſtributing his gifts,<note place="margin">Pſa. 130.1.2.3 Ier. 23.5.6. Matth. 28.18.</note> and diſpoſing of all things for the good of Gods choſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtands the performance of Chriſt his Kingly office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the ſpirituall gouernment of his Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the deſtruction of his and their enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtands the ſpirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Partly in collecting and gathering his Church and the members of it,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.12. Coloſſ. 1.13.</note> out of the world, and from vnder the tyrannie of the Diuell,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.7. Ioh. 10.28. Iude epiſt. 1. verſe.</note> Sinne and Death. And partly, in kéeping it, being collected and gathered in the way vnto life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the Lawes of Chriſt his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gouernment by which he gouernes his Church and the members of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, his word, namely, the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Mark. 1.14. Iſa. 53.1. Rom. 3.27.</note> written in the old and new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 31.33. 1. Cor. 4.20.</note>Secondly, the power and operation of his ſpirit in the hearts of his ſeruants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth Chriſt deſtroy the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 14.27. Pſal. 110.1.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By bringing confuſion on them in his owne good time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When doth Chriſt confound his enemies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Partly in this world, <hi>Pſal. 2.9. Pſal. 110.5.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.9. and 110.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.25. 2. Theſſ. 2.8.</note>But moſt fully in the end of this world in the day of iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:21"/>
               <head>Hitherto of the means of deliuerance God hath vouchſafed to man from his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition. Now to the fourth Principle,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</hi>
                  </note> concerning the vſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of thoſe meanes. Namely; What we are to know and beleeue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our participation of Chriſt and his benefits, and how we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is Chriſt and his benefits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailable to vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By being made ours. For as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens riches auaile nothing to helpe vs being in debt vnleſſe they become ours: ſo Chriſt and his benefits, vnleſſe they become ours, profit vs nothing though he be abundantly rich.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How may Chriſt and his benefits be made ours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we be mad one with Chriſt, by the benefit of our vnion with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.53.56. Philip. 3 9.</note> we are made partakers of Chriſt and of all his benefits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are wee vnited to Chriſt and
<pb facs="tcp:18859:22"/> made one with him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As many as are vnited to Chriſt, are incorporated and made members of that myſticall body whereof Chriſt is the head,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.15.16. &amp; cap. 5.30.</note> which the Scriptures ſet foorth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſimilitude of marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What maner of vnion is it where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made one with Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a myſticall vnion, our incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration into Chriſt and vnion with him is a great myſtery.<note place="margin">Epheſ 5.32.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are wee to conceiue of that our myſticall vnion with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus: That our myſticall vnion with him is a moſt néere and reall vnion.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.12.</note> That our whole perſon body and ſoule are vnited to the body &amp; ſoule of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Eph. 5.30. 1. Cor. 6.15.</note> ſo that we are members of his body and of his fleſh and bones. And by his fleſh we are alſo ioyned to his God-head, to his diuine nature; For that whereby we haue fellowſhip with God, ioynes vs to God.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.20.</note> Now by the fleſh of Chriſt we haue our fellowſhip with God.</p>
               <p>Therfore the fleſh of Chriſt doth ioyne vs to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What kinde of vnion is it whereby
<pb facs="tcp:18859:22"/> we are ioyned to Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is not a corporall vnion by tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, mixture, or the like,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.17.</note> but a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vnion, <hi>1. Cor. 6.17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are the meanes by which we are vnited to Chriſt ſpiritually?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Spirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13. 1. Ioh. 3.24. and cap 4.13.</note> one and the ſame Spirit being both in Chriſt and in vs. Firſt in Chriſt and then in vs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, faith,<note place="margin">Ioh, 1.12.</note> for faith alſo knits vs to Chriſt, and by faith wee receiue Chriſt and his benefits offered vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith is a ſpeciall gift and grace of God beſtowed on his choſen &amp; wroght in their hearts,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.8. Coloſſ. 2.12. Tit. 1.1. Ioh. 1.12. Rom. 5.17. Gal. 3.27.</note> by the power of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whereby they doe apprehend and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Chriſt and all his benefits to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues particularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth a man apply Chriſt to himſelfe ſeeing Chriſt is now in heauen &amp; he heere on earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The applying of Chriſt is by an inward perſwaſion of the heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.3.</note> a man being verily and particularly perſwaded by the effectual perſwaſion of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:23"/> that his ſinnes are forgiuen,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16. 1. Cor. 2.12.</note> and that God is his gracious and merciful Father in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How ſhall a man know that he is ſo perſwaded by the perſwaſion of the Spirit of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By theſe two notes eſpecially.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if he finde in himſelfe a loue to God becauſe of Gods loue to him, and that he loues God, becauſe God hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him firſt.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly if he finde himſelfe inwardly rebuked for euery known ſinne, and that he giues himſelfe no liberty to continue in any knowen ſinne.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are Gods choſen brought truely to beleeue in Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God doth firſt prepare their harts, that they may be fit to receiue faith; and then he worketh faith in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth God make their hearts fit to receiue faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By mollifying, ſoftning, and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their hearts.<note place="margin">Ezech. 11.19. Hoſ. 6.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is the heart of man mollified and ſoftned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By being humbled and caſt downe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth God humble and caſt downe the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By working in man a knowledge and ſight of his ſinnes both originall and actuall and a true ſorrow for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How comes a man to haue a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſight of his ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the morall law of God, <hi>Rom. 3.20. and Rom. 7.7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What is the morall law of God.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that law that was firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart of <hi>Adam</hi> in the time of his innocency, and ſince that; in tables of ſtone in the daies of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34.28. Deut. 4.13. &amp; chap. 10.4.</note> and ſo publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and committed to the Church for all ages, commonly called the decalogue or ten commandements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Where finde we the morall Law of God publiſhed and ſet downe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of it (namely) the ten Commandements we finde written <hi>Exo. 20</hi> from the <hi>3. verſe</hi> at the beginning of it, to the end of the <hi>17. verſe,</hi> but expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in many places of Scripture. For ſo often as the Prophets and Apoſtles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of vertues and vices, they bee the true Interpreters of the Law, &amp; Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:18859:24"/> himſelfe expounds ſome of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>Matth. 5.21.22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee now I am come to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but I purpoſe not to ſtand on them at large; heereafter God willing I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat more at large on them, only now I will ſhew in generall what ſinnes a man may find in himſelfe by the ten Commandements in order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the firſt Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, his deniall of God, his thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king there is no God at all, <hi>Pſalm. 14.1.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalm. 10 4.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, his acknowledging of ſome thing to be his God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 51.12.13. Philip. 3.19. Epheſ. 5.5. Coloſſ. 3.5. Ier. 17.5.</note> which indéede is not God, ſetting his affection on it, fearing it, louing it, putting his truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the ſecond Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 8.10.12 16.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, his worſhipping of a falſe God.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.23. 2. King. 16.10 Coloſſ. 2.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, his worſhipping of the true
<pb facs="tcp:18859:24"/> God after a falſe manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the third Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.12. Math. 4.6. 1. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.31.</note> Euen all thoſe wrongs and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities that are offered by him to the name and glory of God by abuſing his titles, word and workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelf by the fourth Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His prophaning of the Sabbath any way,<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.13. Nehe: 13.15.</note> as by doing any thing on that day that ought not to be done: whether it be a worke of his calling, or a worke of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Or by leauing vndone the workes of the Sabbath, which ought to be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the fifth Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His thinking, ſpeaking,<note place="margin">Pro: 30.11. Iude. verſ. 8. Rom: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.30.</note> or doing of any thing againſt the dignitie God hath beſtowed on others in reſpect of age, place, or gifts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What bee the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the
<pb facs="tcp:18859:25"/> ſixth Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His thinking, willing, ſpeaking or doing any thing that may tend to the hurt or hinderance,<note place="margin">Gen: 9.5, 6.</note> either of his owne life or the life of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the 7. Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His thinking, willing, ſpeaking or doing any thing,<note place="margin">2 Cor: 7.1. 1 Theſ. 4.3, 4.</note> to the hurt or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance either of his owne chaſtitie or the chaſtitie of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the eight Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> His hurting or hindering by any v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>full way,<note place="margin">1 Tim: 5.8. 2 Pet: 2 14. 1 Theſſ. 4 6.</note> the wealth or outward g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tate either of himſelf or of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the ninth Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His hurting or hindering of the good name either of himſelfe or of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Math: 7.1. Phil: 4.8. 1. Cor: 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> by any vntrue and vniuſt opinion or report.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the ſinnes in generall that a man may finde in himſelfe by the tenth Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All his euill luſts both originall &amp; actuall,<note place="margin">Ier: 4.14. Math: 15.19. Iam: 1.14.</note> euen all thoſe euill thoughts and motions that are ſtirring in his heart contrary to charitie &amp; the loue of others, though he giue no liking nor conſent to them. <hi>Ier. 4.14. Math: 15.19. Iam: 1.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is a man brought to a true ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the fearefull and terrible curſe of the law of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the curſe of the law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Both temporall iudgment and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal damnation denounced for the leaſt diſobedience and breach but of one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God,<note place="margin">Deut: 27.26. Gal: 3.10. 2 Cor: 3.7.</note> though it be but once in all a mans life, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one thought, without offering any hope of pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is true ſorrow for ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A true touch of conſcience, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of heart,<note place="margin">Luk: 15.21. Ezra 9.6, 7.</note> with a liuely féeling of Gods diſpleaſure for ſin, in ſuch ſort, as a man, vtterly deſpaires of ſaluation in regard of any thing in himſelfe,<note place="margin">Dan: 9.7, 8. Act: 2.37.</note> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth that he hath deſerued euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting confuſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When a man is thus brought to a
<pb facs="tcp:18859:26"/> ſight of his ſinnes, and a true ſorrow for them, and ſo made fit to receiue faith, how doth God worke faith in him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By working certaine inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in his heart as the ſéedes of faith, out of which faith bréedeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe motions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When a man being humbled, and caſt downe vpon the ſight of his ſins, and with true ſorrow for them, doth feele and acknowledge that he ſtands in great need of Chriſt and Gods mercy in Chriſt. <hi>Luk: 1.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk: 1.53.</note> 
                  <hi>Math: 11.28.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Luk. 15.7.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 15.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the ſecond of thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An hungring deſire of that grace that is offered in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math: 5.6. Ioh. 7 37. Reuel. 21.6.</note> and a longing to be made partaker of it, as a man hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and thirſts after meat and drinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d of thoſe motions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.24. Heb. 4.16.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſlying from the ſentence and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Law and an approching to the throne of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q How doth a man being humbled and ſorrowing for his ſinne, approach to the throne of grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two waies: firſt, by an humble
<pb facs="tcp:18859:26"/> confeſſion of his ſins before God,<note place="margin">Pſalm: 32.5. 2 Sam. 12.13. Luk. 15.18.</note> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, if they be knowne, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, if they be vnknowne.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by crauing pardon of his ſins with vnſpeakable ſighes &amp; groanes,<note place="margin">Hoſea 14.2, 3. Rom. 8.26. Pſalm: 51.1.</note> and ſending vp loude cryes to heauen for Gods mercy in Chriſt, neuer ceaſing ſo to do till the deſire of his hart be granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What followes after theſe motions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After theſe motions, God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne gracious promiſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints in the heart of a poore ſinner,<note place="margin">Iſai. 65.24. Iob 33.26. Matth: 7.7. 1 Tim. 1.15.16.</note> by the worke of his holy ſpirit, a ſpeciall &amp; particular perſwaſion of his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him in Chriſt, and that his ſins are forgiuen him for Chriſt his ſake, and this ſpeciall and particular perfwaſion is a true and a liuely faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Is euery true beleeuer, in like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and degree perſwaded of Gods loue towards him in Chriſt, and of the pardon of his ſins?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.17. Luk. 17.5.</note> there be different degrées and meaſures of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the ſmalleſt meaſure of true faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a perſwaſion in the heart of
<pb facs="tcp:18859:27"/> one truly humbled for his ſins, that his ſins are pardonable, and therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the pardon of them,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> and with his heart euen with ſighes prayeth to God, for the pardon of them, and this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led little faith or weake faith, which is like ſmoaking flax,<note place="margin">Iſai: 42 3. Mat: 17.20.</note> and like a graine of muſtard ſéede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the greateſt meaſure of true faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a full perſwaſion of the heart, whereby a Chriſtian makes full account that God loues him in Chriſt particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Rom: 4.20.21 &amp;c. 8.38.39.</note> and will beſtow on him in particular Chriſt and all his graces that pertaine to eternall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When comes a Chriſtian to this full perſwaſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal: 23.1, 2, 3, 4, 6 2 Tim: 4 7, 8.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not at the firſt, but after the ſenſe, obſeruation, &amp; long experience of Gods loue towards him in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How may a man know that his faith is true and vnfaigned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the fruits of it which are good works. <hi>Galat: 5.6. 1. Tim: 1.5. Iam: 2.18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are the benefits that a true beleeuer receiues by his faith in Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Perfect reconciliation with God,<note place="margin">Rom: 3.25. 1. Cor: 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Act. 15.9.</note> iuſtification in the ſight of God, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is it to bee iuſtified before GOD?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> It is to be accounted iuſt in the ſight of God through the obedience of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Rom: 5.19. &amp; cap. 10.4. 2 Cor: 5.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtands our iuſtification in the ſight of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the remiſſion of our ſins.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, in hauing Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes imputed to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the remiſſion of our ſins?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is our diſcharge and fréedome from the guiltineſſe and puniſhment due to our ſinnes by the merits of Chriſt his death and ſufferings.<note place="margin">Col. 1.21, 22 1 Pet. 2.14. 1 Ioh: 1.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is it to haue Chriſt his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes imputed to vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is to be accepted before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of God,<note place="margin">Philip, 3.8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rom. 4. man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> verſes. 2 Cor: 5.21.</note> and to be accounted worthy of eternall life, by the merits of Chriſt his righteouſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Doe not the good workes of true beleeuers make them worthy of eternall life?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: they doe not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are not perfectly good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.2. Iſai. 64.6. Gal: 5.17.</note> but ſtained with ſin, and imperfect through that corruption of nature, that remaines in true beléeuers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. To what vſe then ſerue good workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſerue to theſe thrée pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat: 5.16. 1. Pet. 2.12.</note>Firſt, to glorifie God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.10.</note>Secondly, to make our calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure to our ſelues. and</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.23, 24.</note>Thirdly, to the profit and good of our brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What followeth on iuſtification in the ſight of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Adoption is euer annexed to it, which is a power and priuiledge to bée actually accounted the children of God,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.5. Ioh 1.12. Galat. 4.5.</note> by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is it to be ſanctified?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tit 3.5. 2 Cor. 3.18. Epheſ. 4.24.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is to be inwardly changed, and renued in nature according to the image of God, in righteouſneſſe and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>How is ſanctification wrought?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the power &amp; vertue of Chriſt his death and reſurrection,<note place="margin">Rom. 6 4.5. Coloſſ. 2.12.13.</note> being made effectuall to ſuch as are iuſtified by the diuine power and working of the holy Ghoſt, hee thereby creating holineſſe in their hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein ſtands the worke of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two things. In mortification or dying to ſinne, and in viuification or quickning to newneſſe of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is mortification or dying to ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a part of ſanctification, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the power, tyrannie and ſtrength of naturall corruption is weakned,<note place="margin">Rom 6.6. 1. Pet. 4.1.</note> and by little and little aboliſhed by vertue of Chriſt his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is viuification or quickning to newneſſe of life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is another part of ſanctification,<note place="margin">Epheſ 2.1. 1 Cor. 15.45. Philip. 3.10.</note> wherby inherent holineſſe, being begun, is ſtill increaſed more and more by the vertue of Chriſt his reſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. In what part of man iuſtified is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification wrought?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In euery power and faculty of his
<pb facs="tcp:18859:29"/> ſoule,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.23.</note> and in euery part and member of his body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Is ſanctification wrought in all true beleeuers equally and at all times alike?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: it is wrought in true belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers differently and by degrées, and it is wrought in them in this life, only in part, and ſhall not be perfected in them,<note place="margin">Rom 8.23. 1. Cor. 13.9. 2. Pet 3.18.</note> before the end of this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the effect or exerciſe of ſanctification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is repentance. For no man can or will truly repent, except he be iuſtified and endued with true faith. Though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance doe firſt ſhew it ſelfe in ſuch as be truely conuerted, yet in the order of nature it followeth faith &amp; ſanctification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a turning from ſinne to God, or a thorow change of the purpoſe of the heart and courſe of life from euill to good.<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.16.17. Ezech: 33.11. Acts 26.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Whence coms this thorow change?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor 7.9.10.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From a godly ſorrow, or a ſorrow according to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is a godly ſorrow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſorrow for ſinne, whereby a man is greeued for no other cauſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:18859:29"/> onely for this, that by his ſinnes, he hath diſpleaſed God, who hath beene to him a gracious and mercifull Father. Thus it was with<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal: 51.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; thus it was with<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> and thus it was with the<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 7.44. compared with 47,</note> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be the things that follow Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two: Firſt, a continuall ſtriuing againſt ſinne, a reſiſting of all motions and temptations to ſin,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.4. Epheſ. 4.27. Iam 4.7. 1 Pet. 5.9.</note> whether comming from our owne corruption, or from the ſuggeſtion of Sathan, or from the enticements of the world, euen to bloud if need require.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Matth: 3.8. 1 Pet: 3 10.11</note> a bringing foorth of new fruits, worthy amendment of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How ſhall a man know that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is true and vnfained?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the generality of it in theſe two reſpects: Firſt,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> verſ: 128. Pſal. 139.24.</note> if it extend to the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring and ſhunning of all knowen ſins. Secondly, if it reach to the practiſe of all good duties that concerne him according to his meaſure of grace and ſtrength gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him.<note place="margin">Palm: 119.6.128.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When is Repentance to bee pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The practiſe of it ought to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall, euen to day before to morrow, and continually.<note place="margin">Heb. 3 7.13. 1 Pet 4.2.</note> Yet at ſometimes there ought to be more ſpeciall practiſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.1 &amp;c.</note> as after great and gréeuous ſinnes committed: In feare of ſome iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hanging ouer our heads for our ſins.<note place="margin">Amos 4 12.</note> Or when wee would fit our ſelues for receiuing of ſpeciall mercies.<note place="margin">Gen. 35.1.2.3 &amp;c.</note> Thus it was with <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What are the ſignes of renued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance after great fals?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are ſeauen, ſet downe <hi>2. Cor. 7.11.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, a care to leaue ſinne into which a man hath fallen.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a cléering of our ſelues, that is, an vtter condemning of our ſelues for the ſame, and a crauing pardon for that ſinne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, an holy anger and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt our ſelues for our careleſneſſe in falling into ſinne.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a feare, leſt wee fall into it againe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, a deſire euer after to pleaſe God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:30"/>
               <p>Sixthly, a zeale to that purpoſe, ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our deſire to walke with God, and to feare and pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, puniſhment and an holy reuenge vpon our ſelues, for that ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fifth Principle.</hi> Touching the ordinarie and vſuall outward meanes of obtaining faith, &amp; all good things that come by faith, &amp; of the encreaſing of it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What outward meanes muſt we vſe for the obtaining of faith, and all good things that doe follow faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The hearing of the word of God preached.<note place="margin">Prou. 29.18. Rom. 10.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the word of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the will of God reuealed néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be known to ſaluation, ſet forth in the holy Scriptures, and written in the bookes of the olde and new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Are all things needefull for vs to know to ſaluation, contained in the holy Scripture?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes: For God being full of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3 15.16.17.</note> hath in them ſet downe whatſoeuer is requiſite for vs to
<pb facs="tcp:18859:31"/> know to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doe we know that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are the word of God and the will of God reuealed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By many infallible notes, as by the purity, the perfection, the antiquity, the maieſty of them in plainnes of ſpéech, and the conſent of one part of Scripture with another, but eſpecially by theſe two notes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by the euidence of the Spirit imprinted in the Scripture,<note place="margin">Epheſ: 1.13.</note> and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs that they are the very word of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by the power of them ouer the conſcience, and the wonderfull effect of them being truely preached, we ſée in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>perience they doe humble men, and throw them downe as low as hell,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12 1 Cor:14.24.25.</note> and then raiſe them vp againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What neede is there of hearing the word preached, ſeeing we may read it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut: 18.17. Rom: 1.16.</note> For two reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it is the ordinance of God, and his power to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee haue néede to haue the word not only propounded in groſſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:18859:31"/> alſo expounded,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14. Act 8.30 31, 2. Tim. 2.15.</note> rightly diuided and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the miniſtery of it, by ſuch as are called to that office.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the vſe of the word of God preached?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In reſpect of Gods choſen it ſerues.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To bréed faith in their hearts:<note place="margin">Rom. 10 14.17. Rom. 1.17.</note> and</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then to encreaſe it.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the reprobate it ſerues thorow their owne corruption,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> as an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their further damnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How muſt the word of God prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched be heard, that it may be effectuall to ſaluation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, with an hungry heart,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2. Iam: 1.19.</note> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it as the food of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>Secondly, with attention.<note place="margin">Acts 16.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, mixing it with faith.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Heb: 4.2.</note> ſubmitting our ſelues to it in feare and trembling,<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.2.</note> euen when wee are iuſtly reproued.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, hiding it in our hearts,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.11. Luk. 11.28.</note> that we may frame our liues and conuerſations by it.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:32"/>
                  <head>Of the Sacraments in generall.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What other outward meanes muſt be vſed for the encreaſing and confirming of faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 4.11. Rom: 9.14.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The receiuing of the Sacraments, and prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> For by the Sacraments faith is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtrengthned and doth more fully, and comfortably apply Chriſt and his benefits vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is an holy ordinance of God, which he hath appointed to be vſed in his Church, adioyned to the preaching of the word,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.11. 1 Cor: 11.12. &amp;c.</note> whereby Chriſt and his benefits are by ſuch outward rites as he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, ſignified, exhibited, and ſealed to them,<note place="margin">Galat: 3.1. Rom: 4.11.</note> that truely beléeue in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What things are to bee conſidered in a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the parts of it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the agréement and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe parts,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>What be the parts of a Sacrament?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two; The ſignes appointed
<pb facs="tcp:18859:32"/> to be vſed: and the things whereof they are ſignes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are thoſe ſignes that are to be vſed in a Sacrament diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: They are either repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſignes, as the outward elements that are to be vſed in a Sacrament: Or applying ſignes, as the actions that are to be vſed about thoſe elements in the adminiſtration and receiuing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
                  <p>Theſe we ſhall ſée when we come to handle the Sacraments ſeuerally.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How many Sacraments be there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two and no more (namely) Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Why be there only theſe two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and no more?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe Chriſt the maker and Mediator of the new couenant, ordained theſe and no more as ſeales of that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, becauſe we can haue no more inward grace applyed to vs,<note place="margin">1 Cor: 10.1, 2, 3. &amp; cap. 12.13.</note> than Chriſt and his ſauing graces which are fully repreſented and ſealed vp vnto vs in theſe two Sacraments.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What difference is there betweene Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Beſides the difference in the ſignes and ſacramentall rites; there is this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwéene them.</p>
                  <p>Baptiſme is a Sacrament of new birth of entrance into couenant with God,<note place="margin">Tit: 3.5. Gen. 17.11. Rom. 6.3. Mat: 28.19.</note> of incorporation &amp; ingrafting into Chriſt, and of admiſſion into the Church of God, and therefore we are once onely baptized.</p>
                  <p>But the Supper of the Lord, is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of confirmation of faith, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing Gods couenant with vs,<note place="margin">2 Chron: 30.6.8. 1 Cor: 10.2, 3, 4. 1 Cor: 11.24, 25.26.</note> and of ours with God, and of further nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of our ſoules to eternall life, and therefore we are often partakers of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the Sacrament of Baptiſme.</hi> Come we to the Sacraments ſeuerally, and first of Baptiſme.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a Sacrament of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, wherein by the Miniſters once waſhing with water in the name of the
<pb facs="tcp:18859:33"/> Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, is repreſented and ſealed to the right Receiuer the powerfull waſhing of the blood of Chriſt &amp; of the Spirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math: 28.19. Epheſ. 5.26. Ioh: 3.5. Galat: 3.27. 1. Cor: 6.11.</note> and ſo his engrafting into Chriſt, his new birth and his entrance into the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What bee the parts of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſignes appointed to be vſed in it, both repreſenting and applying, and the things whereof they are ſignes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What repreſenting ſignes be there in this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Onely one (namely) the outward element of water,<note place="margin">Ioh: 1.31. Act: 8.30.38. Epheſ. 5.26.</note> ſet a part by the word of God and prayer to an holy vſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What bee the things ſignified by water in Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The blood of Chriſt and the ſpirit of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.25, 26, 1. Cor. 6.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſtands the proportion between the water in baptiſme, and the bloud of Chriſt and the ſpirit of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as materiall water ſerues to waſh away the filthineſſe of the body,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.7. Ezech. 36.25.</note> ſo the blood of Chriſt, that is, the force of
<pb facs="tcp:18859:34"/> his death, and the ſpirit of Chriſt, ſerue to clenſe the ſoule of a right Receiuer of Baptiſme from the filthineſſe of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What be the applying ſignes in the Sacrament of Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are the action of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the action of the party baptized.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the action of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the action of waſhing, by dipping or ſprinkling the body of the party baptized,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26. Act. 8.36. Math. 28.19.</note> with the element of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the name of the Father, the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What are the things ſignified by the Miniſters waſhing, by dipping, or ſprinkling of the body with the element of water?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, a ſprinkling of the ſoule of the party baptized with the blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 22.16.</note> to the waſhing away of the guilt of all his ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, a clenſing of his ſoule by the Spirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Tit: 3.5. Rom: 6.3, 4, 5.</note> from the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſin, which is his ſpirituall rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration or new birth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſtands the proportion between
<pb facs="tcp:18859:34"/> the outward waſhing by dipping, or ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling with water, and theſe ſpirituall things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as waſhing by dipping or ſprinkling with water, doth indéed clenſe the body, and take away the filthineſſe of the body,<note place="margin">Ro: 3.24, 25. Rom: 5.9. 1. Cor. 6.11.</note> ſo the blood of Chriſt (that is) the merit of his death applyed and receiued, and the ſpirit of Chriſt being powerfull in the party baptized, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede clenſe the ſoule both from the guilt and from the filthineſſe of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the action of the party baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is twofold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the offering and the giuing of his body to be waſhed with the water of baptiſme, by the hand of the Miniſter.<note place="margin">Act. 8.36.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is ſignified by that offering and giuing his body to be waſhed with the water of baptiſme, by the hand of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The conſecrating and giuing of himſelfe to the Lord, promiſing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue all his promiſes, and to obey all his commandements, &amp; vtterly to renounce
<pb facs="tcp:18859:35"/> the fleſh,<note place="margin">1. Pet: 3.21.</note> the world, and the diuell, <hi>1. Pet: 3.21.</hi> there called the ſtipulation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation of a good conſcience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond action of the party baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the receiuing of the outward waſhing by water, as appeares likewiſe in the <hi>Eunuch. Act. 8.38.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 8.38.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſignifieth that receiuing of the outward waſhing by the water?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A receiuing of the inward wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing by the blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mark. 16.16. Act. 8.37. &amp; cap. 10.43. &amp; 48. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</note> and by the ſpirit of Chriſt, the party baptized belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in Chriſt and repenting of his ſins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Doth the inward waſhing alwaies accompany the outward waſhing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: though God for his part do euer offer it at the preſent to all,<note place="margin">Ezech: 24.13. 1 Cor 10.2.5. 1 Pet. 1.2. Gal. 3.27.</note> yet only Gods elect do effectually partake of that inward waſhing, and that whenſoeuer by the ſpirit and by faith they are vnited to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How farre forth doth Baptiſme being effectuall to Gods choſen, clenſe them for ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It clenſeth them from the guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all their ſins,<note place="margin">1. Cor: 6.9, 10, 11.</note> both originall and
<pb facs="tcp:18859:35"/> actuall,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.7. Iſa: 1.18.</note> and as well committed after bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme as before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What neceſſitie is there of being partaker of the ſacrament of Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There is not an abſolute and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neceſſitie of it to ſaluation; for want of baptiſme when it cannot be had doth not condemne, but the contempt of it when it may be had, yet that is a pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinne: but there is a neceſſitie of baptiſme in part, and that in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, in reſpect of Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment who hath inioyned vs to vſe it.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, in regard of our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who haue néede of all helps that may ſtrengthen our faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Who are to be admitted to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as be in the couenant in likelyhood, or in the iudgement of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Who be thoſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Either perſons of riper yeares that ioyne themſelues to the true Church of God,<note place="margin">Act. 2.38. &amp; cap: 8.37.</note> and make profeſſion of the true faith of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:36"/>
                  <p>Or infants borne of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, for infants of beléeuing Parents are in the couenant of grace<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> according to the promiſe of God,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 2.39. 1. Cor: 7.14.</note> and the promiſe belongs to all beleeuing Parents.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the Lords Supper.</hi> Now to the other Sacrament, <hi>(namely)</hi> the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is alſo a Sacrament of the new Teſtament, wherein by the Miniſters bleſſing and deliuering of bread &amp; wine according to the inſtitution of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 26.26, 27, 28. Luk. 22 19, 22 1. Cor: 11.23, 24, 25, 26.</note> is ſignified, exhibited and ſealed to the right Receiuer, the nouriſhment of the ſoule to eternall life, by the body and blood of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt crucified, and ſo his further growth in Chriſt and his further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the couenant of grace.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What be the parts of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſignes appointed to be vſed
<pb facs="tcp:18859:36"/> in it both repreſenting and applying, and the things whereof they are ſignes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What be the repreſenting ſignes in this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are two, (namely) bread and wine bleſſed and ſet apart, by the recitall of the promiſes of God and prayers vſed to that purpoſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.27 1 Cor. 11.26.</note> from their common vſes to an holy vſe in the Sacrament, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in the inſtitution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What bee the things ſignified by bread and wine in the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The body of Chriſt and blood of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſtands the proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the bread and wine in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper and the bodie and bloud of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as bread and wine ſerue by Gods bleſſing on them to preſerue the naturall life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.15.</note> and to ſtrengthen the body of man: So the body and bloud of Chriſt (that is)<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.54.55. verſ. 48.</note> the merit of his death and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his paſſion ſerue to nouriſh and ſtrengthen both the body and ſoule of the right receiuer of this Sacrament to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:18859:37"/> life. And for this cauſe Chriſt cals himſelfe the bread of life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Why bee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re two repreſenting ſignes in the Sacrament of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For two reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that wee might know that in Chriſt we haue whole and perfect ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall nouriſhment, and whatſoeuer is requiſite to ſaluation.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.54.55.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, for a more liuely repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt his death and paſſion,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.34.</note> in which his bloud was ſeparated from his body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>What be the applying ſignes in the Sacrament of the Supper?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The action of the Miniſter and the action of the Receiuers of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the action of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is twofold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 26.26. Mark 14 22. Acts 2 42. &amp; 20 7.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The breaking of the bread and the powring out of the wine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſignifieth the breaking of the bread and the powring out the wine in the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The breaking of the body of Chriſt and the ſhedding of his bloud, that is,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.24. Mark. 14.24.</note> his enduring of infinite torments in his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both in his body and ſoule for Gods choſen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſtands the proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the breaking of the bread and the powring out of the wine in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and the breaking of the bodie of Chriſt, and the ſhedding of his bloud?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as the bread is broken and the wine powred out, that they may bee receiued to the refreſhing and nouriſhing of the body.</p>
                  <p>So Chriſt his body was broken and his bloud ſhed on the croſſe (that is) hee ſuffered infinite torments on the croſſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> that he might bee receiued by true belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to the comfort &amp; nouriſhing of their ſoules to life eternall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q What is the ſecond action of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the giuing of the bread broken and the wine powred out, into the hands of the Receiuers, <hi>Mat. 26.26.27. Mark. 14.22.23. Luk. 22.19.20.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is ſignified by the Miniſters giuing of the bread broken and the wine powred out into the hands of the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus much: that God doth offer Chriſt his body and bloud to all, yea, to hypocrites, and giueth his body &amp; blood, indéede, to the right Receiuers of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to nouriſh their ſoules to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.32.50.51.</note>For together with the ſignes God doth truly offer the thing ſignified.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſtands the proportion between the Miniſters giuing of the bread broaken and the wine powred out, into the hands of the receiuers, and the action of God, his offering of the body and bloud of Chriſt to all, and giuing of Chriſt his body and bloud to the right Receiuers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as the Miniſter giues the bread and wine to euery Communicant ſeuerally, ſo God doth offer euery one ſeuerally,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6 32. 1. Cor. 10.16.</note> and doth giue to euery right Receiuer particularly the body and blood of Chriſt, that is, the merit of his death and the benefits of his paſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the action of the Receiuer
<pb facs="tcp:18859:38"/> of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is twofold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the taking and receiuing of the bread and wine in to his hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſignifieth the taking and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the bread and wine into his hand?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A ſpirituall apprehending and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the body and bloud of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12. cap. 6.35.</note> (that is) the merit of his death by the hand of faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond action of the Receiuer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the eating of the bread, and drinking of the wine to the nouriſhment of the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſignifieth the eating of the bread and drinking of the wine in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A ſpirituall féeding on the body and bloud of Chriſt, that is,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.56. 1. Cor. 10.16. Epheſ. 3 17. 1. Ioh. 5.10.12.</note> an applying of the merit of his death by faith to the comfort and nouriſhment of the ſoule to eternall life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Is our feeding on the body and bloud of Chriſt in the Sacrament, onely
<pb facs="tcp:18859:39"/> ſpirituall and not corporall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes verily; though Chriſt his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud be truly giuen and receiued in the Sacrament, yet they are not giuen and receiued corporally,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> but ſpiritually and ſacramentally.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How may it appeare that Chriſt his body and bloud are not corporally giuen and taken in the Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we receiue the body and blood of Chriſt in the Sacrament as the Diſciples of Chriſt did in the firſt inſtitution of it.</p>
                  <p>And the body and bloud of Chriſt were not corporally receiued by them, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiritually.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Chriſt his body is aſcended and taken vp into heauen, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens muſt containe him till the end of the world.<note place="margin">Acts 3.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Chriſt hath but one body, and that a true body,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14. Matth. 28.6.7 Luk. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9. Ioh. 20.27.</note> and ſuch as cannot be in many places at once, and it filleth a place whereſoeuer it is, and may be both ſéene and felt <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:39"/>
                  <head>Thus farre touching the ſubſtance of the Sacrament: Now concerning the Perſons who are or may be partakers therof.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Who are to be partakers of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All that haue béene baptized, and are of yéeres and ſound iudgement,<note place="margin">Ezod. 12.26.27. 1 Cor. 11.27.28.29.</note> and able to examine and prepare themſelues, that they may come vnto it worthily.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ought euery Chriſtian when hee comes to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to examine and prepare himſelfe, that he may come vnto it worthily?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hee ought to ſearch and trie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whether he haue in him thoſe things that are required in euery worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat are thoſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are ſixe in number.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 16.15. Pſal. 110.3. Rom. 12.11:</note> The firſt is an holy deſire of the Sacrament and a cheerefull comming to it.</p>
                  <p>For in all the duties of Gods worſhip
<pb facs="tcp:18859:40"/> chéerefulneſſe is required.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond is a meaſure of ſound knowledge,<note place="margin">Prou. 19.2. 1. Cor. 11.29.</note> touching the things and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in and about the Sacrament and the vſe of them.</p>
                  <p>For without knowledge the heart cannot be rightly affected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The third is a true and a liuely faith in Ieſus Chriſt crucified.</p>
                  <p>For in the Sacrament Chriſt is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to vs in no other eſtate,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.26.27.28.</note> then that he was in when he was on the croſſe, as appeares in the firſt inſtitution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The fourth is true and vnfained repentance.</p>
                  <p>For the heart or life, being defiled with any known ſinne,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> not repented of, it pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth and defileth all the holy things of God to that party.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. VVhat is the fift?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> An vnfained and a godly purpoſe of amendment of life.<note place="margin">Pſal. 85 8. Pſal. 119.106.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>VVhat is the ſixt.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A loue to God for his mercy, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
<pb facs="tcp:18859:40"/> in the great worke of our redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and a loue to all that beare the image of God, and eſpecially to ſuch as are renewed according to the image of God in holineſſe and righteouſnes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10 16.17. Ioh: 13.34, 35</note> and are the members of Ieſus Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                  <p>For in this Sacrament we make open profeſſion of our vnion with Chriſt and with his Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ought euery Chriſtian to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe in the receiuing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> With reuerence and ſéemely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of his body, with diligent attention to that which is done during the time of the whole action.<note place="margin">Pſal: 5.7. 1. Cor. 14.40. Act. 1.14. cap. 2.46.</note> and</p>
                  <p>With a ſerious conſideration of the things &amp; actions vſed in the Sacrament. And a thankefull remembrance of the death of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q How ought euery Chriſtian to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe after the receiuing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.57. Ioh 15.5.</note> He muſt endeauour vnfainedly to finde and féele the fruit of it in himſelfe (namely) an increaſe of faith in Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:41"/> and of his loue to all Gods children.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> A greater meaſure of dying to ſinne, and a greater care to liue in newneſſe of life. For none touch Chriſt with a true faith,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.28.30.</note> but they receiue vertue from him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of Prayer.</hi> Hitherto of the Sacraments. Now to the other meanes of increaſing and confirming of faith (namely) PRAYER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Prayer is an humble, hearty and holy requeſt made according to God in will,<note place="margin">Philip. 4.6: Dan. 9.8.9 1 Sam. 1.15. Pſalm. 42.4. 1 Ioh. 5.14. Ioh. 14.14. 1 Tim. 2.1.2.</note> and offered vp by faith to God in the name of Chriſt, for things néedefull either for body or ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What neceſſitie is there of vſing prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Prayer is neceſſary in foure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects eſpecially.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſalm. 50.15. Matth. 7.7. 1 Theſſ. 5.15.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt is becauſe God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond reſpect?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond is for the ſupply of our
<pb facs="tcp:18859:41"/> wants. For euery one wanteth many things, both ſpirituall and temporall, and where ſhould we ſéeke for ſupply of our wants, but at the hands of God, the foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine of all goodnes,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> the author and giuer of all good things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the exerciſe of our faith, <hi>Matt. 6.41. watch and pray,</hi> that is, be vigilant and carefull in the practiſe of this dutie, that ye may be ſtronger in faith, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to reſiſt the force of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That wee may enioy the Lords promiſe of helpe, deliuerance, protection,<note place="margin">1 King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.25. Matth. 7.7. Luk. 7.13.</note> and ſpirituall graces, and good things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. To whom muſt wee direct our prayers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To God alone; euen to one God in Trinity and none other, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, hee,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1. Pſal. 115.3. Epheſ 3.20. Philip. 1.4.6.</note> to whom prayer belongs muſt be able &amp; willing to giue vs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we pray for, but God onely is ſo.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in him to whom wee pray there muſt be knowledge of our hearts.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe prayer ſometimes is <hi>(ſuſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb facs="tcp:18859:42"/> cordis)</hi> but a ſigh or ſecret lifting vp of the heart.<note place="margin">Exod. 14.15. 1 Sam. 1.13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 1.14. Rom. 8.27.</note>But the Lord is the onely ſearcher of the heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note>Thirdly, prayer muſt goe no further then faith.</p>
                  <p>But we muſt beléeue onely in God.</p>
                  <p>Therefore to God onely muſt wee pray.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. In whoſe name muſt we pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 16 24.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the name and mediation of Chriſt only, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.15.16.</note>Firſt, we are commauded in the word of God to pray to God in the name of Chriſt onely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.13.14. 2 Cor. 1.20.</note>Secondly, in the name of Chriſt only we haue promiſe to be heard.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.1.2. Rom. 8.34 1. Tim. 2.5.</note>Thirdly, Chriſt is the only Mediator betwéene God and man, both of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and interceſſion.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, in Chriſt alone, wee are made the children of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.5.</note> and haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to call him Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is it to pray in the name of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is to beſeech God to heare our prayers, not for any thing in vs, or any
<pb facs="tcp:18859:42"/> other, but onely for the merits of Chriſt Ieſus continually offered to him for vs. <hi>Dan. 9.18. Heb. 10.19. &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 9.18. Heb. 10.19. &amp;c.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. In what manner muſt we pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the right forming and framing of prayer three things are required.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt, is knowledge add vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; we muſt know what things may lawfully bee aſked, and how God will haue them aſked: wee may not aſke things ſimply promiſed, with condition,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.14. 1. Cor. 14.15.</note> as ſpirituall things appertaining to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life and ſaluation. Nor temporall things, which are promiſed with condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may we pray for abſolutely or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 143.6. Mark. 11.24. Rom. 10.1.</note> The ſecond is an earneſt deſire of grace for the ſupply of our wants.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The third is aſſurance to be heard,<note place="margin">Mark. 11.24. 1. Ioh. 5.14.15 Iam. 1.6. Pſal. 55.22.</note> ſubmitting our ſelues to the wil of God, for the time, and for the manner of gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our requeſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>Whereupon is our aſſurance to bee heard, grounded?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> On two things:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, on the promiſe of God, <hi>Pſal. 50.15. Pſal. 65.2.</hi> and</p>
                  <p>Secondly, on the mediation of Chriſt. <hi>Ioh. 16 23. Heb. 4.15.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What things muſt we pray for?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Only for thoſe things, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the glory of God and our good in this life, &amp; our euerlaſting ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the life to come, all which things are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in that forme of prayer which Chriſt hath giuen vs, namely, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> ſet downe <hi>Matt. 6.</hi> from <hi>verſ. 9.</hi> to the <hi>14. Luk. 11.2.3.4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What are the things there preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to be prayed for?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe ſix.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that Gods name may bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that hée may rule and raigne in vs by his word and ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that wee may both doe and ſuffer what he willeth, with willingneſſe and chéerefulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that hee would giue vs all things néedfull for this life, and that we may depend and rely vpon his good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:43"/> for all the meanes of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, that for his infinite mercies ſake, he would forgiue vs all our ſinnes, and receiue vs graciouſly into his fauor.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, that he would be preſent, with vs, with the power of his grace, and ſtrengthen vs againſt all temptations vnto euill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. For whom muſt we pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For our ſelues and for others, <hi>Pſa. 50.15. Iam. 5.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. May we pray for all other men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> For all man-kinde or all men, as they make one whole body together, we may not pray but for others yet liuing in the world, of all ſorts, places and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoeuer,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1. 1 Ioh. 5.16.</note> we may pray vnleſſe it be apparant that any one hath ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of geſture in Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What geſture of body muſt be vſed in praying?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Such as doth beſt expreſſe and ſhew forth the inward reuerence, humilitie,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:44"/> earneſt deſire and affiance of the hart,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.39. Luk 22.41. Epheſ. 3 14. 1. King. 8.54. Lam. 3.41. Ioh. 17.1. 1 Sam. 1.10. 2 King 20, 3.</note> as caſting downe the body, bowing of the knées, lifting vp of the hands and eyes to heauen, ſhedding of feares and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Are theſe geſtures alwaies neceſſary in praying?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: they are not abſolutely and alwaies neceſſary,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13. Pſalm. 6 6. 2 Sam 7.18. Pſal. 143.8. 1. Cor. 14.40.</note> ſo that the heart be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp to God, and nothing bee done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt good order, and vnbeſéeming the company with whom we pray, or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. In what place muſt we pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Praier may be made in euery place, it's not tyed now to any one place, more then to another in regard of holineſſe; but onely in reſpect of order,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.8. Mal. 1.11. Ioh. 4.20.11. Acts 21.5.</note> as the publike place of méeting for the worſhip of God, beſt fitteth common prayers, and a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate place beſt fitteth priuate prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. When muſt we pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Continually and at all times. <hi>1. Theſſ 5.17. Epheſ. 6.18. Luk. 18.1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How muſt we pray continually?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: either by ſet and ſolemne prayer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.17. &amp; 92.2.</note> and that vpon ſet and ſolemne oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as at the beginning of the works
<pb facs="tcp:18859:44"/> of our callings,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.17. 1. Tim 4 4 5.</note> at the receiuing of the creatures of God, as meat, drinke and ſuch like, or at our going to reſt, or vpon a ſudden by a ſecret lifting vp of our hears to God,<note place="margin">Nehem. 2.4.</note> according to the preſent occaſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Muſt ſet and ſolemne prayer be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely at ſet times, and vpon ordinary occaſions?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: it muſt ſometimes be vſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily, and we muſt ſomtimes ſet apart more then ordinary time, and giue our ſelues wholly to ſolemne prayer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. 164. Hoſea 14.3. 1 Cor. 7.5.</note> as when we either feare ſome great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or heauy iudgement to come vpon vs: or when it is already come on vs; or when wee would obtaine ſome néedefull grace either for body or ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>What help muſt we vſe to make vs pray more earneſtly on extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The exerciſe of faſting, <hi>1. Cor. 7.5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is faſting?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is an abſtaining from all ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the body,<note place="margin">Ioel 26. Ezra 8.21. Heſter 4.16. Neh. 1.4.</note> and from all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the ſenſe for a time, that therby we may bee fit, thorowly to humble our
<pb facs="tcp:18859:45"/> ſelues, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d more earneſtly to ſeeke the face and fauour of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Now to the ſixt Principle.</hi> Touching the eſtate of man after hee hath led a ſhort life heere in this world.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. After a man hath liued heere in this world for a time what followeth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the enemie of nature, or the end of naturall life,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26.</note> euen a ſeparation of the ſoule from the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Muſt all men die?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes verily, all, both good and bad, both the godly and true beléeuers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.19. Pſal. 89.48. Eccieſ. 2.16. Heb. 9.27. 1 Cor. 15.51.</note> and the wicked and vnbeléeuers muſt dy, ſaue onely ſuch, as ſhall bee found aliue at Chriſt his comming to iudgement, to them a change ſhall be in ſtéed of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q Death being a puniſhment of ſinne, how is it that the godly and true beleeuers die, to whom all ſinnes are forgiuen?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Death to the godly and true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers is not a puniſhment of ſinne, but through the death of Chriſt, a good thing and a bleſſing of God, and that in thrée reſpects.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it giues reſt to them, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers them from all the painefull labours and miſeries of this world;<note place="margin">Act. 7.60. 1 Cor. 15.18. 1 Theſſ. 4.13.14. Reuel. 14.13.</note> and hence it is called a ſleepe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it is an vtter aboliſhing of ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.7.</note> and the accompliſhment of their mortification.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, it is a paſſage and entrance, by which their ſoules enter immediately into heauenly glory.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.7. Luk. 16.22. &amp; cap. 23.43. Philip. 1.23. 2. Cor. 5.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What followeth immediately on the death of euery man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, particular iudgement, namely,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> the ſentence of particular abſolution, or of particular condemnation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the conueyance of the ſoule immediately by the power of God and the miniſterie of Angels,<note place="margin">Luk. 16 22.23</note> into a ſtate ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of happineſſe or miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſhall follow after particular iudgement?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18859:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A day of generall iudgment, at the ſecond comming of Chriſt, wherein all men that euer haue béene,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.14. Mat: 12.36. Act: 17.31. 2 Cor: 5.10.</note> are now, or ſhall be hereafter, ſhall be iudged, and euery one ſhall receiue according to his works.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When ſhall the day of generall iudgment be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The time of it is vncertaine, no man can know or ſet downe the day,<note place="margin">Mat: 24.36. Mar: 13.32. Act. 1.7.</note> wéeke, moneth, yéere or age wherein it ſhall be: Chriſt himſelfe as man in the daies of his fleſh had no expreſſe notice of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why is the time of that day of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall iudgment vncertaine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. to the end of the 6. verſe.</note>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That from the vncertaintie and ſuddenneſſe of it, we might learne to bée alwaies prepared and ready for it.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Signes foreſhewing the laſt iudgment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſignes be there foreſhewing the laſt and generall iudgment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſignes foreſhewing it are of two ſorts.</p>
                  <p>Some going before and further off from the comming of Chriſt to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:18859:46"/> and ſome néerer to his comming and ioyned with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What are the ſignes foregoing and further off from Chriſt his comming to iudgment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Mat: 24.14.</note> the publiſhing of the Goſpell throughout the whole world.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.3. 1 Tim: 4.1.</note> an apoſtacie and departure of moſt men from the faith and from the truth of Religion.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 4, 8. 1. Ioh. 2.18.</note> the reuealing of Antichriſt the man of ſin and child of perdition.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Mat: 24.12, 37, 38, 39. Luk. 17.26, to the 30. &amp;c 2 Tim. 3.1. 1. Theſſ. 5.3.</note> common corruption in the manners of men, with ſecuritie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding deadnes of heart.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, great and gréeuous calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the world and in the Church. <hi>Matth: 24.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 24.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">Rom: 11.25.</note> the calling of the Iewes to the faith of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What are the ſignes neerer to the comming of Chriſt to iudgment and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſhaking of the powers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the darkning of the Sunne and Moone,<note place="margin">Mat: 24.29, 30.</note> the falling of the ſtarres from
<pb facs="tcp:18859:47"/> heauen,<note place="margin">2 Pet: 3 7, 10, 11.</note> the firing of the whole frame of heauen and earth, and the diſſolution of the whole world, which is called the ſigne of the Sonne of man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall follow after theſe things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math: 24.30. Act 10.42.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The comming of Ieſus Chriſt, who ſhall be Iudge of the whole world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. In what manner ſhall Chriſt come to iudgment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall in his humane viſible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuddenly like lightning breake forth through the heauens,<note place="margin">Act: 1.11. Mat. 24.27.30 2 Theſſ. 1 7. 1 Theſſ: 4.16. Iude verſ: 14 Mat: 25.31.</note> and come in the clouds, with great maieſtie and glory, with an infinite hoaſt of elect Angells, and with the voice and ſhout of an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angell, and the trumpet of God, and ſhall ſit downe on the glorious throne of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall follow after that Chriſt is ſet in his throne of iudgment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The citing and preſenting of all men both quicke and dead,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.32. Iude verſ. 6.</note> and the deuils alſo before his glorious throne to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall all men be cited to iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the voice of Chriſt vttered by
<pb facs="tcp:18859:47"/> the miniſterie of Angells,<note place="margin">Ioh: 5.25, 28, 29. Mat. 24.31. 1 Cor: 15.52. Iob 19.16.27</note> euen by that ſhout and trumpet of the Archangell, which ſhall be ſo powerfull, as that it ſhall change the liuing in the twinkling of an eye, and cauſe all the dead to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, euery one with his owne body and euery part and parcell thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Shall the elect and reprobate bee raiſed from the dead without any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: though they ſhall both be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſame almighty voice &amp; power of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh: 6.54. 1 Cor. 15.20, 22, 45.</note> yet it ſhall be with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: The elect ſhall be raiſed as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt his body, by vertue of his reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>But the reprobate ſhall be raiſed by the power of Chriſt, as he is a Iudge, and by vertue of Gods curſe ſet downe <hi>Gen: 2.17.</hi> that that ſentence may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified on them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Shall the dead riſe againe in the ſame bodies wherein they liued on the earth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes verily, in the ſame bodies for ſubſtance, but altered in qualitie,<note place="margin">2 Cor: 5.10. 1 Cor: 15.52, 53.</note> and made immortall and incorruptible, and
<pb facs="tcp:18859:48"/> able to abide for euer in that ſtate, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they ſhall be adiudged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What difference ſhall there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the bodies of the elect and of the reprobate being raiſed from the dead?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This difference.</p>
                  <p>The bodies of the Elect ſhall be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.43, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 44, 49. Philip: 5.21.</note> powerfull, frée from all paſſion and ſuffering, and like vnto the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But the bodies of the reprobate, ſhall be on the contrary, full of vncomelineſſe and vgly to looke on,<note place="margin">Dan: 12.2. Ioh. 5.29.</note> agreable to the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of their conſciences, and lyable to ſuffer extreame torments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall all men be preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt his throne of iudgment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 21.28. 1. Theſſ. 4.17.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The elect ſhall with great ioy be caught vp into the ayre to méet the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And the reprobate, with the deuill and his Angels,<note place="margin">Luk: 21.26. Reuel: 6.15, 16, 17.</note> ſhall with extreame horror and confuſion, be forced to come before him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What neede is there, that the dead ſhould be brought to iudgement, ſeeing particular iudgement was giuen of them before, whether they be good or euill?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is néedfull for two cauſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe that firſt iudgment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines only to the ſoule,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> but the latter to the whole man, both to body and ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that that particular iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be made manifeſt before all men, and that there may be a more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt declaration of Gods iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall follow after that all men and euill Angels are cited and ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A ſeparation of the elect from the reprobate.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.32.33</note> Chriſt ſhall then ſet the elect as ſhéepe on his right hand, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate as goates on his left hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall follow, after that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The act of iudgement wherein the elect ſhall be firſt acquitted,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.54. Luk. 22.30. 1. Cor. 6.2.3.</note> and then by way of approbation ſhall ioyne with Chriſt in iudging of the reprobate both men and Angells.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall Chriſt proceede in the act of iudgement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: He ſhall firſt examine and try euery mans particular cauſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:18859:49"/> after tryall and examination made, giue ſentence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall euery mans particular cauſe be tryed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By his workes. <hi>1 Cor. 3.13. 2 Cor. 5.10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Why ſhall men be tryed at the day of iudgement by their workes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe workes are open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſignes &amp; teſtimonies either of faith,<note place="margin">Matth. 12.36.37. Iam. 2.18.</note> or of vnbeléefe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall mens workes bee then made manifeſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: the Lord who certainly knoweth all the thoughts, words, and works of men, ſhall then by his mighty power ſo enlighten the conſcience of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one,<note place="margin">Reuel. 20.12. Rom. 2.16.</note> as it ſhall perfectly remember whatſoeuer good or euill he or ſhee hath done in the time of this life,<note place="margin">1 Cor 4 5.</note> the ſecrets of all hearts being then reuealed, and this is called the opening of the booke of conſcience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall mens works being made manifeſt, be tryed whether they be good or euill?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two waies.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe waies?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt is this, they ſhall be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the law of God, which hath béene reuealed to men, whether it be the law of nature only,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.12.</note> which ſerues to leaue them without excuſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 2 16. Ioh. 12.41.</note> who neuer heard of Chriſt; Or the written word of GOD vouchſafed to his Church as the rule of faith and life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond of thoſe wayes?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2, 15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The euidence of euery mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing witnes with him or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. After tryall and examination of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans cauſe how ſhall Chriſt giue ſentence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall according to the euidence of conſcience touching works giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſaluation to the elect, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of damnation to the reprobate,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.34.41.</note> adiudging them with the deuill and his angells to the curſe of euerlaſting fire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Shall men bee adiudged to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or damnation for the merit of their workes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Sentence of damnation ſhall bée giuen on the reprobate, they being out of
<pb facs="tcp:18859:50"/> Chriſt for the merit of their workes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note>Becauſe their workes are perfectly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and deſerue damnation.</p>
                  <p>But on the elect ſentence of ſaluation ſhall be giuen for the merit of Chriſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and applied to themſelues by faith.<note place="margin">Iob. 5.24. Iam. 2.18. Gal 5.6. Ioh. 3.26.</note> And they ſhall be pronounced iuſt.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe their good workes though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect doe approue their faith to bee a true faith working by loue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q After Chriſt hath giuen iudgement on the elect and reprobate, what ſhall follow?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The execution of iudgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall iudgement be executed on the elect and on the reprobate?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: Chriſt by his Almighty power and commanding voice, ſhall ſend the reprobate with the Diuell and his Angels into hell, and bring Gods Elect into the poſſeſſion of life &amp; glory in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.28. Matth. 25.46.</note> After Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Come yee bleſſed children of my Father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world: and depart from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire prepared for the Diuell and his Angels:</hi> Then it
<pb facs="tcp:18859:50"/> followeth, and theſe ſhall goe away into euerlaſting puniſhment; but the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous into life eternall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. In what ſtate ſhall Gods Elect be in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall enioy vnſpeakable; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiueable and euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe in the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are wee to conceiue of that bleſſednes, as the word of God hath made it knowen vnto vs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: that it ſhall be a moſt happy and a moſt bleſſed ſtate,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.8. Ioh. 3.2. 1. Cor. 15.28. Reuel. 21.3.23.24. and cap. 22.1.2.3.4 5.</note> wherein the elect being moſt fully ioyned to Chriſt their head ſhall enioy the preſence of God, and ſhall ſée and behold the face and glory of God, and haue ſpeciall fellowſhip with God, and God himſelfe ſhall bee to them thorow Chriſt all in all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What bee the parts of that beſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two: eternall life, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to conceiue of that life eternall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: It ſhall be ſuch a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God, as that God himſelfe ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:18859:51"/> be thorow Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.19.20 23. Coloſſ. 3.3.4. 1 Ioh. 4.15.</note> life to all the Elect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately quickning them by his ſpirit, and that for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall be the condition of that life eternall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The condition of it ſhall be in two things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt of thoſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 25.8. 1. Cor. 5.54. Reu. 7.16.17. and cap. 21.4.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This: it ſhall be frée from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of miſeries, and all manner of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It ſhall haue a full and perpetuall ſufficiency in it ſelfe of all good things,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.9. Reuel. 21.23. Reuel. 22.5.</note> ſeruing to make a moſt bleſſed life née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding none of the meanes of this life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to conceiue of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect glory in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: It ſhall bee a wonderfull and vnſpeakable excellency of the Elect, whereby they ſhall bee euen as Chriſt himſelfe,<note place="margin">Luk. 20.36. Philip. 3.21. Coloſſ. 3.4 1. Ioh 3.2. Reuel. 21.11.</note> although vnequally &amp; in a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degrée, yet aboue meaſure glorious, and in their ſoules and bodies in a farre more excellent eſtate, then any heart can wiſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall bee the glory of the
<pb facs="tcp:18859:51"/> ſoules of Gods Elect in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12. Epheſ. 5.27. Reuel. 3.45. Reuel. 19.8.</note> they ſhall be endued with a perfection of knowledge, wiſedome and holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall be the glory of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Gods elect in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This:<note place="margin">Matth. 13.43. Luk. 20.36. Philip. 3.21.</note> they ſhall bee endued with perfection of beauty, brightneſſe, maieſty and ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. <hi>What ſhall bee the glory of Gods Elect in heauen belonging both to their bodies and ſoules?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A,</hi> This: they ſhall bee as Princes crowned with crownes of glory,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8. Reuel 22.5. Matth. 35.34. Rom. 16.20. 1. Pet. 1.4. 2. Pet. 3.13.</note> and raigning with Chriſt for euer, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing ouer Sathan, death and hell, and haue poſſeſſion of that new heauen and new earth, wherein dwelleth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Shall all Gods Elect haue the ſame degree of glory in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No:<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3. 1. Cor. 15.21.22.</note> though euery one of Gods choſen ſhall receiue the full meaſure of glory, whereof they ſhall be capable, yet one ſhall haue a greater degree of glorie then another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall a greater degree of glory
<pb facs="tcp:18859:52"/> be giuen in heauen, to one of Gods Elect then to another?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> According to the greater meaſure of graces giuen and the more faithfull employment of thoſe graces,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.28.29 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cor. 9.6. and cap. 4.17. Reu. 7.14.15.</note> either in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, or in ſuffering for the truth of Chriſt, in the time of this life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q What ſhall be the fruits of both the parts of bleſſedneſſe, namely, of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life and perfect glory?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The fruit ſhall be twofold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11. and 36.8. Ioh. 16.20.22</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Fulneſſe of vnſpeakable and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 7.15.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The perfect and perpetuall ſeruice of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Wherein ſhall that perfect and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſeruice of God conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In a continuall acknowledging of Gods vnſpeakable mercy towards them in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 4.10.11. Reu. 5.12.13. Reu. 11.16.17</note> and in a continuall lauding and praiſing of his great and holy name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. After what manner ſhall Gods elect ſerue and worſhip God in heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By God himſelfe immediately, néeding neither Temple, Ceremony, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,<note place="margin">Reu. 21.22.</note> nor any outward thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:52"/>
                  <head>Of the miſery of the <hi>Reprobate in hell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall be the ſtate of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> They ſhall haue vnſpeakable,<note place="margin">Mat. 23 41 46</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiueable, and euerlaſting miſery in the fire of hell.</p>
                  <p>For as neither eye hath ſéen, eare hath heard, heart hath conceiued, or tongue is able to expreſſe the ioyes of the Elect in heauen:</p>
                  <p>So certainely, neither eye hath ſéene, eare hath heard, or tongue is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the miſery of the damned in hell fire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How doth the Scripture ſet foorth that miſery to vs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By things terrible and fearefull and to bee abhorred,<note place="margin">Dan. 12:2. Mar. 9.43.44. Matth 25.41. Reu. 19.20. &amp; cap. 20.15. Mat. 8.12. &amp; Mat. 13.42.</note> as by ſhame and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting contempt, by the worme that neuer dieth, by the lake burning with fire and brimſtone, by fire that neuer goes out, by vtter darkneſſe, by wéeping and
<pb facs="tcp:18859:53"/> wailing and gnaſhing of téeth and the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to conceiue of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of the Reprobate in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus, that it ſhall bee a moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and a moſt wretched eſtate, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Reprobate being for euer ſeuered from the comfortable preſence of God and glorious fellowſhip of Chriſt and his Saints,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.23. Luk. 13.27.28 Matth. 25.41. 2. Theſſ 1.9.</note> and hauing eternall fellowſhip with the Diuel and his Angels, ſhall féele the whole wrath of God vpon them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What bee the parts of that miſerie of the Reprobate in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two (namely) eternall death and euerlaſting ſhame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are wee to conceiue of that death eternall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: that it ſhall be ſuch a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Reprobate from God,<note place="margin">Reu. 2.11. Reu. 21.8. 2. Theſſ. 1.9.</note> as that their miſery ſhall be as a continuall death: wherein they ſhall be alwayes dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and neuer dead, and this is called the ſecond death and eternall perdition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall be the condition of that death eternall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The condition of it ſhall bee two ſold.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the firſt condition of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This: it ſhall bee voide of all good things, and of all manner of comfort,<note place="margin">Matth. 22.13. 2. Pet. 2.17. Iud: verſ. 13.</note> and this is ſhadowed out by vtter darkneſſe, and by blackneſſe of darkneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond condition of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This:<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.33. Matth. 13.42. Luk. 16.23.24 &amp;c.</note> it ſhall haue a perpetuall fulneſſe of all euils and all manner of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries without the leaſt meanes of eaſe or remedy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to concciue of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſhame in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: it ſhall be a wonderfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable vileneſſe of the Reprobate,<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.24. Dan. 12.2. Reuel. 22 25.</note> whereby they ſhall be euen as the Diuell himſelfe aboue meaſure odious &amp; abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and in their ſoules and bodies in a more baſe and vile condition then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans heart can conceiue; they ſhall be as dogs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Shall all the Reprobate haue the ſame degree of wretchednes and miſerie in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: although every one of them, ſhall haue the full meaſure of miſery,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.25. &amp; 11.22.24.</note> wherof they ſhall be capable, yet one ſhall haue a greater degrée of miſery then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How ſhall ſome of the Reprobate haue a greater degree of miſerie then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> According to the greater merit of their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.47.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Matth. 23.14.</note> either in reſpect of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or quality of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What ſhall be the fruit of both the parts of that miſery of the Reprobate in hell, namely, of eternall death and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſhame?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The fruit ſhall be twofold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 25.46. Luk. 16.23.14 Rom 2.9. Mar. 9.43.44.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Fulnes of vnſpeakable and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torment both of their ſoules and bodies. <hi>Iud. verſ. 6. Reu. 20.10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A continuall and a moſt horrible and deſperate wéeping, howling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out in conſideration of the happines of the Saints of God in heauen, which they ſhall ſée and enuy;<note place="margin">Matth. 8.12. Matth. 13 42. Luk. 13.28. Luk. 16.23.24.26</note> and in reſpect of of their owne endleſſe miſery and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, out of which they ſhall haue no hope to eſcape.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thus in part wee haue heard what ſhall be the ſtate of Gods Elect in heauen, and of the Reprobate in hell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18859:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the principall end of the bleſſedneſſe of the Saints of God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and of the miſerie of she Reprobate in hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The glory of God,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.4. Rom. 11.36.</note> who in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall purpoſe and decrée, hath fore-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained all things to his owne glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to conceiue of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall decree touching men and Angels?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: that it is his free appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and fore-ordaining them,<note place="margin">Rom 9.22.23 1. Theſſ. 5.9.</note> for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and euerlaſting eſtate for his owne glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What be the parts of that decree of God touching men and Angels?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two: Election and Reprobation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is election?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.21. Epheſ. 1.5.6.</note> It is the Lords frée ordaining of ſome both men and Angels to euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe for the declaration and glory of his goodneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is reprobation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the Lords frée ordaining of ſome,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.22. 2. Tim. 2.20.</note> both men and Angels to eternall ſhame and diſhonour, for the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and glory of his iuſtice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
